Today's video is a science video about
how to create various milks and creams
using the highest fat cream you can find
in your local store. So, as it's a
science video,
this is as this is as much as I can put
it on. Let's do food science.
Obviously, that is for my kid. She's
five. Let's um
That is as good as it gets. Yeah, making
milk and cream is surprisingly easy.
Obviously, if you're just making milk,
you know, 2% or skimmed milk or you or
whole milk, just buy the milk powder and
then make it up as per the directions
for that. There are ways to save you
huge amounts of money doing this, and
it's pretty simple. So here in Canada or
specifically southern Alberta where I
live, a gallon of milk, this much milk
is $7, just under Canadian. This much
cream is also $7. We can make
three of these with this and water and a
little bit of skim milk powder. The skim
milk powder will actually only cost
about $4 or $5 the amount we're going to
use. So you can save a huge amount of
money doing this. Why do we need skim
milk powder? We need skim milk powder to
bring the milk solids back in line. And
the milk solids is the protein and the
lactose. That's what creates milk's
texture. Uh cream, the higher fat you
go, the less of a problem it kind of
becomes. So lactose is in is a water
soluble sugar. So it's a water it's only
soluble in the water element of your
milk. So if you remove the the whey the
water element of milk, you remove all of
that lactose too. So let's just say we
want to make 3.5% milk, whole milk if
you will. By making it this way, we get
to remove 98% of the lactose from the
milk by using cream, water, and then a
solids booster. The solids booster, if
you want to keep that lactose down, you
can use soy milk powder. And then we can
mask that nutty flavor with vanilla
extract. If you're not bothered by
lactose, add some skim milk powder to
it. Those calculations are available in
the file I've made available to Patreon
members and YouTube channel supporters.
It's really that simple. In these three
glasses, I'm going to use 33% whipping
cream, which is the highest standard
available cream to me here. I can get
36% if I go into Calgary, but I just
don't want to do that. 3.5% milk, 10%
cream, 18% cream. All right. And that
covers super easy the 10% and the 18%
cream. Honestly, they're designed
inadvertently for perfect ninja creamy
recipes. So, that's why we're going to
do this. And the final ingredient we're
going to need, like I said before, is
that skim milk powder. If you want to
keep that lactose down, use soy milk
powder as discussed. There's our skim
milk powder. Let's get a spoon. Spoon
and tiny whisk. Let's go. So, in our
first glass, we're going to make 3.5%
milk. So, we're going to weigh this out.
I will put cup measurements for you. I
mean, it's it's pretty difficult doing
cup measurements for such a small amount
here, but in the file, there will be cup
measurements in there. It's pointless
doing cup measurements for a point, you
know, 200 mls worth of stuff.
Experimental amounts. This is what I'm
doing this for. So, 3.5% milk in here.
What do we need? We need simply 21 grams
of our 33%
cream.
Not a lot. 21 grams to make 10%.
So half and half here in Canada is 10%
fat. We need 60 g of our cream.
And then finally to make 18% cream. All
these glasses weigh different amounts.
We need 109
g.
There we go. That's our cream. So, let's
lay these out so we don't get confused.
Back to our whole milk. Let's zero that
out.
So, here we go. Straight cold water
right out of tap. You probably just
heard me running that tap. So to make
our 3.5% whole milk into our 21 grams of
cream, we're adding 178 gram of water.
Perfect. And then for our 10% cream, we
are adding 140 g of our water.
And finally
for our 18% cream we are adding 90 g of
water.
Is there enough?
No.
Now into these. So remember whole milk
10% fat cream 18% fat cream. We need to
boost the solids in the lower fat
versions more than the higher fat
versions. So, we're going to take
one two teaspoons of skim milk powder
goes into our whole milk. One teaspoon
of whole milk powder goes into our 10%.
We actually don't need any in the 18%,
but if you really want to, half
teaspoon. Again, I will reiterate this.
If you don't want the lactose that is in
skim milk powder, of which there is
about 50% of it is lactose, use soy milk
powder. This is soy milk powder. I get
it from Bulk Barn. It's incredibly cheap
beers, like 85 cents per 100 g. You're
using a tiny amount. So if you're making
one liter of, say, 10%,
then you're only using 3540 g of this
stuff, not a lot. So if you want to make
large batches, you know, like 4 lers of
ultra low lactose, 10% fat cream,
do this. And then you can hide the the
nutty taste of soy milk powder using
vanilla extract. There we go. Let's get
our tiny whisk.
[music]
And there we have quite simply the
easiest way to make variations in fat
content of milk and cream. It's that
easy. This is whole milk.
I mean, it tastes delicious. Tastes
exactly like whole milk. That's what it
is. This is our 10% cream.
Obviously creamier than our whole milk.
And our 18% cream.
Perfect
cream all around my face. That is it.
It's incredibly easy. Money saving
through the wazoo. If financial savings
are important to you, like I said, you
can save a huge amount of money making
milk like this. Buy skim milk powder
from Bulk Barn. It's pretty cheap. I
actually get mine in bulk from a
commercial supplier, but get it on
Amazon. There are some incredibly
expensive versions and variations of
skimmer powder. I don't know why people
want to charge that much for it, but if
you're in Canada, go to um supertore.
It's there. It's cheap. Doesn't have to
be a fancy brand. All skim milk powder
is the same. As long as it's 0.1% fat or
less, then it's perfect for this.
multiple cream variations right here in
front of you. They are all perfect for
making ultra quick ninja creamy luxury
gelatoes and ice creams. And not just
ninja creamy, you can use these for any
churned style ice cream. You can use it
for coffees. You can you literally the
the world is your roster. The file is
available to all of you beautiful
Patreon supporters of which there is a
long list here and all YouTube members.
If you're a YouTube member and you can't
get access to that image that I will put
on screen in a post for you, then just
hit me up and I will send you a link to
it. That is it, my glorious friends. The
absolute easiest way to make any cream
available to you. If you're in the UK
and you got 50% cream, I I'm super
jealous. Calculations are in this file
as well, so you can make whatever you
want with the best cream on the planet.
So, these are just the examples I've
given you in this video. our whole milk,
our 10% and our 18%. But again, any
variation you can make using this exact
method, the higher the fat content of
the product that you're making, the less
ski milk powder you need. That 18%
doesn't even need that skim milk powder
in it. But just to create something
super luxurious, absolutely do. If you
don't want to use soy milk powder cuz
you just don't like the taste, like I
said, you can hide that nutty flavor
using some vanilla extract. And there's
a sweet spot for how much you need to
use. And that is about 5 g of vanilla
extract per 750 gram or milliliters of
milk and or cream. That gets rid of that
flavor. If you don't want to use soy
milk powder, absolutely use coconut milk
powder. It will impart a slight coconuty
taste, but obviously the higher the fat
cream that you're making, the less of it
you actually need to use. 18%. If you go
to 20%, you don't need to add any solids
booster to it at all. So, no powders, no
skim milk powder, no uh soy milk powder,
no coconut milk powder. You don't need
to do any of that. It's really only the
milks and the lower cream. So, the 10%
that you really need to boost that
solids content. But with that in mind, I
hope you find this video useful. Make
any cream or milk in the world at home
using what you have. Thanks very much
for watching. Don't forget to like and
subscribe and I'll see you next week
when I'm going to do a Ben & Joe's
remake cuz I've been meaning to do one
for bloody ages and next week is going
to be it. So bye.